Guide to the Lighthouse Photograph and Print Collection [1860]-1938 PR 38
New-York Historical Society
- Series II: Lighthouses
  - American Lighthouses -- New York
    - Great Beds (2 items), 1885 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 37)
    - Hallet's Point, 1883 (Box Unknown container 566 for instance of Hallet's Point, Folder unknown container)
      See: Box 8, Folder 66
    - Hell Gate (2 copies), [1884-1886] (Offsite-box 3, Folder 37)
    - Hell Gate, 1884 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 37)
    - Hudson-Athens (Hudson City), 1886 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 38)
    - Hudson River signal installation, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 38)
    - Huntington Harbor (formerly Lloyd Harbor) (2 copies), 1885 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 38)
    - Little Gull Island (2 items), [1884], 1923 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 38)
    - Livingston Creek (2 copies), 1886 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 38)
    - Montauk Point (4 items, 2 copies), 1884 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 38)
    - New Dorp (Swash Channel Range Rear), [1890] (Offsite-box 4, Folder 39)
    - North Brother Island, 1885 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 39)
    - North Dumpling (2 copies), undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 39)
    - Old Field Point, 1885 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 39)
    - Plattsburgh (2 items), 1886 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 39)
    - Plum Island (Plum Gut), 1884 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 39)
    - Pointe aux Roches, 1886 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 39)
    - Princes Bay, 1885 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 39)
    - Race Rock Light Station, New York Daily News clippings mounted on board (2 copies), 1936 Mar. 27 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 39)
    - Romer Shoal, 1935 Sept. 19 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 39)
    - Rondout, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 39)
    - Sands Point (2 items), 1884 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 40)
    - Shinnecock, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 40)
      See also: Box 7, Folder 66
    - Split Rock, 1886 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 40)
    - Stepping Stones, 1886 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 40)
    - Stony Point, 1886 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 40)
    - Stuyvesant, 1886 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 40)
    - Tarrytown (Kingsland Point), 1886 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 40)
    - Throg's Neck (2 copies), 1884 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 40)
    - U.S. Lighthouse Depot (now the National Lighthouse Museum) -- Administration Building (by Alexander & Tolman), 1890 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 41)
    - U.S. Lighthouse Depot (now the National Lighthouse Museum) -- Aerial view (by Fairchild), 1931 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 41)
    - U.S. Lighthouse Depot (now the National Lighthouse Museum) -- Engineer's and carpenter's store house, [1890] (Offsite-box 4, Folder 41)
    - U.S. Lighthouse Depot (now the National Lighthouse Museum) -- Engineer's lamp shop under construction, [1868] (Offsite-box 4, Folder 41)
    - U.S. Lighthouse Depot (now the National Lighthouse Museum) -- Engineer's lamp shop, 1890 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 41)
    - U.S. Lighthouse Depot (now the National Lighthouse Museum) -- Workshop under construction, [1868] (Offsite-box 4, Folder 41)
    - Valcour Island (Bluff Point), 1886 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 41)
    - West Point, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 41)
    - Unidentified (3 items), undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 41)
  - American Lighthouses -- North Carolina
    - Bodie Island (2 items), 1893 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 42)
    - Cape Hatteras -- Beacon (2 items), 1893 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 42)
    - Cape Hatteras -- Dwelling no. 1, 1893 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 42)
    - Cape Hatteras -- Dwelling no. 2, 1893 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 42)
    - Cape Hatteras -- Tower, 1893 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 42)
    - Cape Lookout (2 items), [1893] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 42)
    - Currituck Beach (2 items), 1893 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 42)
    - Federal Point, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 43)
    - Long Point -- General view, 1893 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 43)
    - Long Point -- Boat house, 1893 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 43)
    - Long Point -- Dwelling no. 1, 1893 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 43)
    - Long Point -- Dwelling no. 2, 1893 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 43)
    - Long Point -- Retort house and gas tank, 1893 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 43)
  - American Lighthouses -- Ohio
    - Cleveland East Breakwater West End (2 items), [1879] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 44)
  - American Lighthouses -- Rhode Island
    - Beaver Tail (2 items), 1884, [1884] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 45)
    - Block Island, [1880] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 45)
    - Bristol Ferry, 1884 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 45)
    - Bullock Point, [1898] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 45)
    - Dutch Island, 1884 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 45)
    - Ida Lewis Rock (formerly Lime Rock), Ida Lewis pictured, 1884 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 45)
    - Newport Harbor (Goat Island), 1884 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 45)
    - Plum Beach, 1884 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 45)
    - Point Judith (2 copies), [1880] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 46)
    - Prudence Island (Sandy Point), 1884 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 46)
    - Rose Island (2 items), 1884, [1884] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 46)
    - Watch Hill, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 46)
  - American Lighthouses -- South Carolina
    - Cape Romain, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 47)
  - American Lighthouses -- Vermont
    - Burlington Breakwater North End, 1886 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 47)
    - Burlington Breakwater South, 1886 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 47)
    - Isle La Motte, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 47)
    - Juniper Island, 1886 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 47)
    - Windmill Point, 1886 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 47)
  - American Lighthouses -- Virginia
    - Unidentified, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 47)
  - American Lighthouses -- Wisconsin
    - Devils Island (2 items), 1893 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 48)
    - Outer Island -- General view, 1893 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 48)
    - Outer Island -- Fog signal houses (2 items), 1893 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 48)
    - Port Washington (4 items), 1893 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 48)
    - Port Washington Pierhead, 1893 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 48)
    - Superior Pierhead, 1893 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 48)
  - American Lighthouses -- Multistate
    - "Lighthouses along the coast between Portland and New York - 'By Sea to Maine'" published by Maine Steamship Company, New York (2 partial copies), [1907] (Box Unknown container 567 for instance of "Lighthouses along the coast between Portland and New York - 'By Sea to Maine'" published by Maine Steamship Company, New York (2 partial copies), Folder unknown container)
      See: Box 7, Folder 67
  - Foreign and U.S. Territorial Lighthouses -- England
    - Bishop Rock (by Alfred Camm), [1880] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 49)
  - Foreign and U.S. Territorial Lighthouses -- Puerto Rico
    - Arecibo (Faro de Arecibo), [1900] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 49)
    - Cape Rojo (Cabo Rojo), [1900] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 49)
    - Cape San Juan (Cabo San Juan), [1900] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 49)
    - Cardona Island (2 items), [1900] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 49)
    - Culebrita Island (Isla Culebrita), [1900] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 49)
    - Guanica (2 items), [1900] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 50)
    - Mona Island (Isla de Mona), [1900] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 50)
    - Muertos Island (Isla Caja de Muertos), [1900] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 50)
    - Point Borinquen, [1900] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 50)
    - Point Jiguero (Higuero), [1900] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 50)
    - Point Mulas (2 items), [1900] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 50)
    - Point Tuna, [1900] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 50)
    - Puerto Ferro (Faro de Puerto Ferro) (2 items), [1900] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 50)
  - Unidentified Lighthouses
    - Unidentified lighthouses, [1890] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 51)
- Series III: Floating Aids to Navigation
  Series III dates from 1884-1927 and consists of photographic and ephemeral materials documenting light vessels, tenders (ships which service buoys), and buoys. Photographs are arranged in two subseries: Light Buoys and Accessories, and Ships and Light Vessels. Light Buoys and Accessories consists of a series of half tone tear sheets and is organized alphabetically according to the manufacturer's name and thereunder by the manufacturer's numbers. The Ships and Light Vessels subseries is arranged alphabetically by ship name with type noted in parentheses when known. Where they can be identified, light vessel (LV) numbers have been given.
  - Light Buoys and Accessories
    - American Gas Accumulator Co. -- Sun Valve, No. 1118, [1904] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 52)
    - American Gas Accumulator Co. -- Beacons -- "Kurinsky Kamenj" No.1238, [1904] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 52)
    - American Gas Accumulator Co. -- Beacons -- "Blockhusudden" No. 1261, [1904] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 52)
    - American Gas Accumulator Co. -- Beacons -- Waalhaven at Rotterdam, No. 1275, [1904] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 52)
    - American Gas Accumulator Co. -- Light Buoys -- For Uruguay, No. 1276, [1904] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 52)
    - American Gas Accumulator Co. -- Light Buoys -- For Roumania [Romania], on Courtney Buoy, No. 1278, [1904] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 52)
    - American Gas Accumulator Co. -- Light Buoys -- For Harlingen, Holland, No. 1457, [1904] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 52)
    - Unidentified Manufacturers -- Built Up Bell Buoy, Goat Island Depot (2 copies), 1916 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 53)
    - Unidentified Manufacturers -- Tompkinsville Gas Buoy (by Lamb), 1927 May 31 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 53)
  - Ships and Light Vessels
    - Amaranth (tender) (4 items), [1897] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 54)
    - Bartlett Reef, LV 13 (light vessel) (by Haskell), 1913 Sep. (Offsite-box 5, Folder 54)
    - Boston,, LV 54 WAL 502 (light vessel) (by Underhill), 1915 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 54)
    - Brenton Reef, LV 39 (light vessel), undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 54)
    - Cornfield, LV 48 (light vessel) (2 copies) (by Haskell), 1913 Sep. (Offsite-box 5, Folder 54)
    - Diamond (light vessel) (by Rosenfeld), [1922] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 54)
    - Dewitt Clinton (tugboat), undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 54)
    - Hyacinth, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 54)
    - Iris (tender), undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 55)
    - John Rodgers (tender), undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 55)
    - Northeast, LV 111 (light vessel), 1926 Dec. 29 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 55)
    - Overfalls, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 55)
    - Putnam (tender), [1890] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 55)
    - Sandy Hook, LV 16 (light vessel), 1884 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 55)
    - Supply Steamer Armeria, 1890 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 55)
- Series IV: Light Station Equipment
  Series IV dates from ca. 1873-1927 and consists of photographs of a variety of types of equipment along with associated equipment tests and exhibitions. The photographs are arranged by type of equipment or related subject into six subseries: Audible Alerts, Engines and Air Compressors, Equipment Tests, Lenses and Lighthouse Apparatus, Lighthouse Equipment Exhibition Displays, and Unidentified and Miscellaneous Equipment.
  Audible Alerts consists primarily of photographs of fog signals. One series of fifteen photographs documents the construction of the fog signal structure and installation of equipment by Hamilton-Foster Fog Signal Co., at Falkner's Island (Faulkner's Island), Connecticut. Four details of fog bell apparatus for the Minots Ledge Light Station in Massachusetts are included.
  Engines and Air Compressors consists of a group of photographs by Underhill of Meitz and Weiss oil engine air compressors as installed in various engine rooms. Also included in this series are photographs of unidentified engine rooms, one of which is in Detroit, Michigan.
  Equipment Tests show details of various equipment tests, including rust tests on steel and iron, tests of centrifugal pumps, and a few tests of machinery under icy conditions.
  Lenses and Lighthouse Apparatus consists of photographs and halftone tear-sheets of lenses and lanterns made by Barbier, Benard & Turenne Manufacturers (Paris, France), Chance Brothers and Co. (London, England), and by unidentified manufacturers. Locations of installed lenses and lanterns have been listed in the finding aid.
  Lighthouse Equipment Exhibition Displays includes photographs of equipment displays at various international exhibitions. Also included is a 1927 typescript letter from the acting Commissioner of Lighthouses to the Department of Commerce regarding lighthouse exhibition photographs from the Sesqui-Centennial International Exhibition in Philadelphia in 1926.
  - Audible Alerts
    - Bialy, John A. - Fog bell for Minots Ledge Light, Massachusetts (4 items, elevations and cross sections), undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 56)
    - Daboll - Rotating fog apparatus, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 56)
    - Hamilton-Foster Fog Signal Co. - Construction of fog signal at Falkner's (Faulkner's) Island, Connecticut (16 items), undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 56)
    - New England Gamewell Co. - Fog bell machine, [1897] (Offsite-box 6, Folder 56)
    - Stevens, George M. (Boston) - Improved fog bell machine, 1897 Mar. 9 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 56)
    - Unidentified manufacturer -- Whistle reflector, [1896] (Offsite-box 6, Folder 56)
  - Engines and Air Compressors
    - Meitz and Weiss Oil Engine Air Compressor Series, Boston, (by Underhill, New York) -- Engine room interiors (B22901- 2 copies, B22902, B22645), 1915 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 57)
    - Meitz and Weiss Oil Engine Air Compressor Series, Boston, (by Underhill, New York) -- Close up of engine components (B22394, B22395, no number), 1915 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 57)
    - Unidentified Manufacturers -- Engine room interior, Detroit, Michigan, [1873] (Offsite-box 6, Folder 58)
    - Unidentified Manufacturers -- Engine room interiors (3 items), undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 58)
  - Equipment Tests
    - A.G.A. Flashing & Reducing Chamber filled with ice, 1914 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 59)
    - A.G.A. Reconstructed Flasher operating while frozen, 1915 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 59)
    - Centrifugal pump testing (2 items), 1922 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 59)
    - Ingot iron and steel rust tests (inscribed as: steel scaled, ingot iron scaled, ingot iron not scaled), [1915] (Offsite-box 6, Folder 59)
    - Valve pressure testing series (4 items), [1897] (Offsite-box 6, Folder 59)
  - Lenses and Lighthouse Apparatus
    - Barbier, Benard & Turenne Manufacturers (Paris, France) -- Cape Hinchinbrook, Alaska - Third order lightning light, 1906 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 60)
    - Barbier, Benard & Turenne Manufacturers (Paris, France) -- Hillsboro Inlet, Florida - Second order bivalve lightning light, 1906 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 60)
    - Barbier, Benard & Turenne Manufacturers (Paris, France) -- Liston Range Rear, Delaware - Range light, 1906 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 60)
    - Barbier, Benard & Turenne Manufacturers (Paris, France) -- Mexican Government - Fourth order lenses (half tone tear sheet) (2 copies), [1890] (Offsite-box 6, Folder 60)
    - Barbier, Benard & Turenne Manufacturers (Paris, France) -- Point Arena, California - First order lightning light apparatus, 1906 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 60)
    - Barbier, Benard & Turenne Manufacturers (Paris, France) -- Unidentified (half tone tear sheet), [1890] (Offsite-box 6, Folder 60)
      See also: Box 7, Folder 68
    - Chance Brother's and Co. (London, England) -- Cape Leeuwin, Western Australia - First order light (halftone tear sheet), [1895] (Offsite-box 6, Folder 61)
    - Chance Brother's and Co. (London, England) -- Cape of Good Hope - First order quadruple flashing light (half tone tear sheet), [1895] (Offsite-box 6, Folder 61)
    - Chance Brother's and Co. (London, England) -- Makapu Point - Lens (half tone tear sheet), 1908 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 61)
    - Chance Brother's and Co. (London, England) -- Mexico - Dioptric lighthouse apparatus, [1875] (Offsite-box 6, Folder 61)
    - Chance Brother's and Co. (London, England) -- Oyster Island, Burma - First order fixed occulting white lens light (by H.J. Whitlock), [1890] (Offsite-box 6, Folder 61)
    - Chance Brother's and Co. (London, England) -- Pulau Pisang, Malaysia - First order lantern, [1890] (Offsite-box 6, Folder 61)
    - Chance Brother's and Co. (London, England) -- Spurn Head, England - Single-flashing hyperradial apparatus (halftone tear sheet), [1897] (Offsite-box 6, Folder 61)
    - Chance Brother's and Co. (London, England) -- Watling Island, Bahamas - Second order double flashing light (by H.J. Whitlock), [1890] (Offsite-box 6, Folder 61)
    - Chance Brother's and Co. (London, England) -- Experimental lantern and apparatus for floating light, [1890] (Offsite-box 6, Folder 61)
    - Unidentified manufacturer -- Bolina Point, Texas - Lens, [1908] (Offsite-box 6, Folder 62)
    - Unidentified manufacturer -- Hawaii - Lens, [1900] (Offsite-box 6, Folder 62)
    - Unidentified manufacturer -- Second order bivalve lens (2 items), [1898] (Offsite-box 6, Folder 62)
    - Unidentified manufacturer -- Unidentified lens, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 62)
    - Unidentified manufacturer -- Unidentified lantern base and wick (2 items), undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 62)
    - Unidentified manufacturer -- Unidentified gas burning navigational lantern, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 62)
  - Lighthouse Equipment Exhibition Displays
    - Paris Exposition Universelle, Paris, France (2 items), 1900 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 63)
    - Panama-Pacific International Exposition, San Francisco, CA, 1915 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 63)
    - Safety First Exhibit, Washington, DC (2 items), 1916 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 63)
    - Sesqui-Centennial International Exposition, Philadelphia, PA (11 items), 1926 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 63)
    - Letter from the acting Commissioner of Lighthouses to the Department of Commerce regarding exhibit photographs, 1927 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 63)
  - Unidentified and Miscellaneous Equipment
    - Light station tool box, 1915 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 64)
    - Vulcan iron and steel works, frame fabrication (2 items), undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 64)
    - Unidentified instrument panel, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 64)
    - Unidentified equipment shop exteriors (3 items), undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 65)
- Series V: Lithograph Album by Julius Bien
  Series V dates from ca. 1860 and consists of a series of 150 lithographs (bearing plate numbers 1-95) bound into one oversize volume measuring 34.5 x 24.5 inches. The album contains plans, sections, and elevations of lighthouse towers, buoys, lamps, lanterns, lenses, light vessels, and other equipment for lighthouse service.
  Julius Bien (1826-1909) was a German-born painter, cartographer and lithographer who immigrated to the United States in 1849. He settled in New York and became known as a one of the country's finest mapmakers. Bien did extensive cartographic work for the United States Government. This album is stamped "U.S. Light House Establishment," and "Col R Delafield Corps of Engineers" is inscribed on the cover. It is presumed that the album was once in the possession of Richard Delafield (1798-1873), who was in charge of New York Harbor defenses from 1861-1864 and was Chief Engineer of the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers from 1864-1866. Each plate in this reads "Lith of J. Bien 60 Fulton Street," an address from which Bien is known to have worked only in 1860.
  - [Specifications for buoys, lamps, lanterns, lenses, light vessels, beacons, lighthouses, and other equipment for lighthouse service. 150 lithographs; plates are numbered 1 through 95.], [1860] (Volume 1)
- From Series II: Lighthouses
  - American Lighthouses -- New York
    - Fire Island, undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 66)
    - Hallet's Point (by I. Almstaed), 1883 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 66)
    - Shinnecock, undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 66)
  - American Lighthouses -- Multistate
    - "Lighthouses along the coast between Portland and New York - 'By Sea to Maine'" published by Maine Steamship Company, New York (2 partial copies), [1907] (Offsite-box 7, Folder 67)
- From Series IV: Light Station Equipment
  - Lenses and Lighthouse Apparatus
    - Barbier, Benard & Turenne Manufacturers (Paris, France) -- Lighthouse equipment (cabinet cards) (2 items), undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 68)